in this example we want to figure out
the probability that if I randomly
choose a number between 3 and 14 where
I'm including the end I'm cluding 3 and
I'm including 14 what is the probability
that an even integer now what I want to
partially illustrate here is that this
questionable probability is
intrinsically tied to the idea of
counting in that that in many ways
answering your probability problem is is
answering a question about counting so
let's pull up the particular integers
that were interested in so I've got 3 4
all the way down to 14 and I've
highlighted in yellow the even integers
so what our formula told us is that I
want to investigate the number of things
in our event so this case the number of
evens happens to be denoted by an E as
well but it stands for event divided out
by the number in our sample space and
that this is going to be the probability
of our event so we have to do these two
counties so let's count the even ones
first I've got 4 6 8 10 12 and 14 so
that looks like 6 even are appearing
here so this is going to give me 6 and
then the total number of things between
3 and 14 is 12 so divided up by 12 here
in other words this is going to be 0.5
or 50% as well but notice that if I
change this question a little bit
suppose I then went and said from all
the way from 3 up to 15 well how does
that change 15 is not an even integer
but it would increase the number down
here from 12 to 13 and so your
probability would change because you've
increased the size of your sample space
even though you haven't changed the
number of even if you haven't changed
the number in your event